בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is קי״ט Kuf Yud Tet
of בבא בתרא Bava Batra 119. We pick up on קי״ט Kuf
Yud Tet about eight lines down at the two dots going to
the משנה, Mishna, back to the משנה: Mishna: ושהיה בכור נוטל פי
שנים. Ve-she-hayah Bechor Notel Pi Shenayim. Since צלפחד Tzelofchad was a בכור,
Bechor, he got two portions. This is the משנה's Mishna statement that
בנות צלפחד Bnot Tzelofchad got three portions, assuming that you go by
יוצאי מצרים. Yotzei Mitzrayim. So one portion he got because he was
יוצאי מצרים, Yotzei Mitzrayim, and then he passed that down to his
daughters once they won their case with משה. Moshe. And then because
his father חפר Chefer was also יוצאי מצרים, Yotzei Mitzrayim, and חפר
Chefer was dead, so חפר Chefer and צלפחד Tzelofchad was a בכור,
Bechor, he got two portions of חפר's Chefer unit that חפר Chefer
would have gotten. So those two portions were smaller portions than the
portion he got, because that was divided up amongst all the brothers,
but anyway he got two portions of חפר's Chefer portion because he
was a בכור. Bechor. So that's the משנה, Mishna, three portions: one
big portion for, you know, normal-sized portion for himself that he passed
down to his daughters, and then חפר's Chefer portion subdivided amongst all
the brothers that he got two parts of that one portion because
he was the בכור, Bechor, and then he also passed down to
his daughters. Okay, so let's take a look at what the גמרא
Gemara says about this. Okay, ואמאי, Ve-amai, now why did he, why
was he entitled to two portions? ראוי הוא, Ra'ui hu, it was
not something that חפר Chefer had come into possession of yet. ואין
הבכור נוטל בראוי כבמוחזק, Ve-ein ha-bechor notel be-ra'ui ke-vi-muchzak, a בכור Bechor
does not get a double portion in things that his father, were
coming to his father, that his father had not yet taken possession
of, right? So let's say, you know, after his father owned a
business, and after his father died, the business made a profit. Okay,
so that was not money that was yet in the possession of
the father, so he would not get two portions. He would only
get a double portion in בכל אשר ימצא לו, Be-chol Asher Yimatzeh
Lo, in everything that the father already had in the father's possession
when the father died. So the father did not yet have his
portion in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael in his possession. It was coming
to him, but he didn't yet have it. So why does חפר
Chefer get double portion of it?
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, בישוב עולם,
be-yishuv olam, we're not talking about his portion in ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, we're talking about a double portion in whatever the father owned.
So he owned ten pegs and he owned two camels and a
cow and a sheep and whatever. Not talking about ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael at all, which is of course not at all the פשט.
pshat. The whole focus here is ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but fine,
he means a double portion in other things that חפר Chefer had.
מתיבי רבה, Masiv Rabba, so רבה Rabba challenged: רבי יהודה אומר בנות
צלפחד נטלו ארבע חלקים, Rabbi Yehuda omer Bnot Tzelofchad natlu arba chalakim,
Rabbi Yehuda says they got four portions, not three. שנאמר, Shene-emar, ויפלו
חבלי מנשה עשרה, Vayipplu Chavlei Menashe Asara, the portion of מנשה Menashe
were ten portions. And we quoted this the other day, and six
of them were divided into, you know, the major tribes, families of
מנשה, Menashe, and four very different sized portions that went to צלפחד.
Tzelofchad. So but regardless, clearly when we're talking about the number of
portions we're talking about portions of the land. And that's clearly the
פשט pshat of everything. Don't tell me we're talking about ten pegs.
אלא אמר רבה, Ela amar Rabba, ארץ ישראל מוחזקת היא. Eretz Yisrael
muchzeket hi. This is a principle that we saw before, that ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you know, is already considered to be in possession
of those that left מצרים, Mitzrayim, and therefore it is not something
that just that is coming their way, it is something that we
are already seen already to have been in possession of. An idea
that we introduced earlier. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, and I think the רשב״ם Rashbam here just quotes the פסוק.
pasuk. Let's take a look at the רשב״ם. Rashbam. מוחזקת היא, Muchzeket
hi, look at three lines down in the widest line. ליוצאי מצרים
כדכתיב ונתתי אותה לכם מורשה, Le-yotzei Mitzrayim kide-chtiv Ve-natati otah lachem morasha,
כלומר אני נתתיה לכם ירושה. klomar ani netatiha lachem yerusha. I have
given it to you as an inheritance, not I will give it
to you, but you already have received it as an inheritance. You
are already in possession of it. It's interesting, right? Not that the
אבות avos are in possession of it, not that the people that
actually took possession of it are in possession, but those that were
יוצאי מצרים yotzei Mitzrayim are already considered to be ארץ ישראל's Eretz
Yisrael in their possession.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. מתיבי, Meitivei, I'll challenge you. אמר רבי חידקא, Amar Rabbi Hidka,
שמעון השקמוני Shimon HaShikmoni היה לי חבר מתלמידי רבי עקיבא. hayah li
chaver mi-talmidei Rabbi Akiva. Okay, I was a colleague with this רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, with this person שמעון השקמוני Shimon HaShikmoni who was
one of the students of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. וכך היה רבי
שמעון השקמוני אומר, Ve-kach hayah Rabbi Shimon HaShikmoni omer, and this is
what he used to say. יודע היה משה רבינו שבנות צלפחד יורשות
הן. Yodea hayah Moshe Rabbeinu she-Bnot Tzelofchad yorshos hen.
משה Moshe of course knew that without any brothers they were entitled
to an inheritance. Not what it sounds like in the פסוקים, psukim,
but we're going to try to say that it can't be that
this major concept was something that משה Moshe did not know. So
it must be that משה... Moshe... did have to consult with God,
but we're going to try to make it smaller, the point of
what Moshe was not aware, rather than the whole idea was something
that they prompted. Now maybe it's because we don't want Moshe not
to be, you know, to have to have this blind spot in
his knowledge, maybe it's rather that it'd be too radical to think
that because of their request such a major new innovation took place,
so we're going to make it more of an issue of a
clarification than an innovation. So Moshe already knew that they were entitled
to a portion if there were no brothers. יודע היה משה רבינו
שבנות צלפחד יורשות הן Yodea haya Moshe Rabbeinu shebenot Tzelafchad yorshas hen
אבל לא ידע אם נוטלות חלק בכורה עם
האבות. aval lo yada im notlot chelek bechora im ha'avot. They did
not know was were they entitled, and of course they were entitled
to the full inheritance of their father that he was going to
get as יוצאי מצרים. yotzei Mitzrayim. What they didn't know was were
they entitled to a double and they were going to stand in
for צלפחד Tzelafchad
vis-a-vis צלפחד's Tzelafchad brothers to get a portion in חפר. Chefer. All
of that Moshe knew. What he didn't know was were they entitled
to a double portion the same way צלפחד Tzelafchad would have been.
Probably, you know, this question about ראוי ra'uy and מוחזק, muchzak, that
was the question he did not know. אבל לא ידע אם נוטלות
חלק בכורה עם האב, Aval lo yada im notlot chelek bechora im
ha'av,
וראויה היתה—he v'ra'uya hayta didn't know whether the הלכה halacha about ראוי
ra'uy and מוחזק muchzak or whether he didn't know the idea whether
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is considered מוחזק מאבותינו, muchzak me'avoseinu, you know,
that already those who were יוצאי מצרים yotzei Mitzrayim were considered מוחזק.
muchzak. That was the one thing and he knew all the הלכות
halachot he just needed a little clarification about that one point. וראויה
היתה פרשת נחלות להחשב על ידי משה V'ra'uya hayta parshas nachalos lehikashev
al yedei Moshe and
therefore because Moshe already really knew all of this, it was just
one little point of clarification, it should have been that Moshe like
the rest of the תורה, Torah, God should have said
וידבר ה' אל משה לאמר, vayedaber Hashem el Moshe lemor, you know,
or Moshe commanded בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael regarding the נחלות, nachalot, it
shouldn't have had to have to have to come through the prompting
of בנות צלפחד, benot Tzelafchad, he knew all of this already. אלא
שזכו בנות צלפחד ונכתבה על ידן, Ela shezaku benot Tzelafchad venichteva al
yadan, but they merited because of their initiative and their love of
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or however you understand it, because they were
צדקניות, tzidkaniyos, they merited that the פרשה parsha was written on their
prompting. But it would have been written even without them. We don't
want to make it seem like without Moshe, you know, without them
this הלכה halacha never would have been taught or that there was
this blind spot that Moshe had.
ויודע היה משה רבינו שהמקושש במיתה. V'yodea haya Moshe Rabbeinu shehamikoshesh bemisa.
Similarly, you know, there's other times when Moshe has to go check
in with God. There's also the case about the קרבן פסח, Korban
Pesach, which we're not going to do פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. Moshe
knew that the person who collected wood on the שבת Shabbat was
deserving of death, שנאמר מחלליה מות יומת. shene'emar mechaleleha mot yumat. I
mean that was clear that the תורה Torah had said he's deserving
of death earlier. אבל לא ידע באיזה מיתה הוא ימות. Aval lo
yada be'eizeh misa hu yamut. What he didn't know was, you know,
what type of death to put him, that he was going to
be put to death,
what type of execution. וראויה היתה פרשת מקושש להחשב על ידי משה,
V'ra'uya hayta parshat mikoshesh lehikashev al yedei Moshe, and therefore you didn't
need it that there had to have been the event of the
gatherer of the wood, which by the way according to some opinions
was צלפחד, Tzelafchad,
you didn't need that to have been that it was only because
of that event that it prompted it to be written, right? Moshe
knew this הלכה, halacha, we don't want to say it was a
blind spot for Moshe, so it would have been written even without
that event. אלא שנתחייב מקושש ונכתבה על ידו. Ela shenitchayav mikoshesh venichteva
al yado. But because of the circumstances, that's why the event, it
happened that this was actually written because, you know, it came out
to be written due to those circumstances, but it would have been
written even without those circumstances.
ללמדך שמגלגלין זכות על ידי זכאי וחובה על ידי חייב. Lelamedcha shemegalgelin
zechut al yedei zakai vechov al yedei chayav. That somebody who is
meritorious, good things, you know, come about as a result of them
even if they would have come about anyway, but now they come
about as a result of that person. So בנות צלפחד benot Tzelafchad
were meritorious, they were צדקניות tzidkaniyos and so on, and therefore even
though it would have been written independent, the circumstances played out that
it was written as a result of their prompting. And the מקושש
mikoshesh of course was somebody that was sinful
and deserving of punishment and therefore something bad, the punishment of a
מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbat was written connected to him and not independent
of him. Okay, now what does that, that's very nice and that's
a famous teaching, what does that have to do with our question
about, about the בנות צלפחד benot Tzelafchad here? ואי סלקא דעתך ארץ
ישראל מוחזקת. V'isalkat daitach Eretz Yisrael muchzeket. Now because this question about
why they got the double portion because ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael was
already considered in possession of those who left Egypt, so if that's
true, מאי קמסתפקא ליה? mai kamistapka lei? So what was his question?
Right, and of course the question is and if it wasn't מוחזקת,
muchzekes, also what was his question, then obviously he shouldn't have gotten
a double portion. But okay, the גמרא's Gemara really rather than asking
a challenge, clarifying. So the גמרא Gemara says: היא גופא קמסתפקא ליה,
Hi gufa kamistapka lei, that's exactly what he had a doubt. Is
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael considered מוחזקת? muchzeket? He knew the הלכה halacha
that if there's no sons, the girls get it. He knew the
הלכה halacha that the girls would stand in in place of their
father and get their father's portion from חפר. Chefer. What he didn't
know was, and he knew the הלכה halacha that a בכור bechor
only gets something that the father is already in possession. session of
חפר Chefer was already in possession of, that all that he knew,
he didn't know whether to consider ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael already to
be in the possession of יוצאי מצרים. yotzei mitzrayim. מאי קא מיסתפקא
ליה? mai ka mistapka lei? האי גופא Hai gufa קא מיסתפקא ליה,
ka mistapka lei, דכתיב dechativ the פסוק pasuk says
ונתתי אותה לכם מורשה אני ה': unatattee otah lachem morasha ani Hashem:
I will give it to you as an inheritance, I am God.
ירושה לכם מאבותיכם. Yerushah lachem me’avoteichem. So do we read that that
it is something that you have already inherited? It is a patrimony,
it is a bequest that you have, a ירושה, yerusha, an inheritance
from your forefathers and you are already when you leave מצרים Mitzrayim
in possession of it? או דילמא, O dilma, or do we read
it שמורישין ואינם יורשין? shemorishin ve’einam yorshin? That מורשה morasha is להוריש.
lehorish. It is something that you will pass on to your children,
you do not—you have not yet inherited it. Okay, so he did
not know how to read that פסוק. pasuk. Does it mean that
they’re considered to already have inherited?
ופשטו ליה תרוייהו, U’pashtu lei tarvaihu, and he learned that both ירושה
לכם מאבותיכם. yerushah lachem me’avoteichem. Okay, excuse me, I read them as
mutually exclusive. I should not have read it mutually exclusive, you know,
it is both an inheritance from your forefathers, you are already in
possession, ומורישין ואינם יורשין. u’morishin ve’einam yorshin. And you also, you know,
you pass this down to the next generation. Okay,
so therefore,
that's what the רשב"ם Rashbam explains this אינם יורשין einam yorshin means.
I was reading it possibly as exclusive, one or the other, either
you get it or you pass it down, but the רשב"ם Rashbam
says no—I mean the גמרא Gemara says they're both true. So what
does it mean אינם יורשין? einam yorshin? אינם יורשין einam yorshin means
that they don't in the end inherit because you won't actually be
going into ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay, and that's actually what the
גמרא Gemara is about to say. So even though ironically you are
already in possession of it, okay, and for the הלכה halacha of
בכור, bechor, so you're already considered to be a
ירושה, yerushah, and therefore חפר's Chefer firstborn is going to get a
double portion. At the same time, only in the capacity of מורישין
morishin will you now pass it down, but you yourself will never
actually—you’re in possession of it enough to give your son צלפחד Tzelofchad
a double portion, but you’ll never actually יורש yoresh it. You will
never actually come into physical possession of it. You will not enter
into ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay, so it's actually quite ironic. So
that's the point that the גמרא Gemara gets to right now: the
idea that the irony or the fact that even as this פסוק
pasuk was said, ונתתי אותה לכם מורשה, unatattee otah lachem morasha, way
at the beginning even before they left מצרים, Mitzrayim, there was already
the hint to the idea that they would be passing it on.
It would be inheritance, but they would pass it on, but ultimately
they would not come into possession of it. Okay, והיינו דכתיב, ve’hainu
dechativ, and that is also what is written: תביאמו ותטעמו. Tavi’eimo v’tita’eimo.
God, You will bring them and plant them in Your holy mountain,
said at the
שירת הים, Shirat HaYam, בהר נחלתך. be’har nachalatcha. תביאנו Tavi’einu לא נאמר,
lo ne’emar, not You will bring us, I משה Moshe and בני
ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, the current generation, אלא תביאמו. ela tavi’eimo. You will
bring
them. מלמד שמתנבאים ואינם יודעים מה מתנבאים. Melamed shemitnab’im ve’einam yod’im mah
mitnab’im. They, those who said שירת הים, Shirat HaYam, would prophesy but
were not aware of what
they were prophesying, that they themselves would not be able to make
it into the land. All right, ותעמודנה. Vata’amodnah. Anyway, but that's the
idea that it was already a ירושה. yerushah. They were already seen
to be in possession of it, even though they would never actually
come into possession of it. And that's how צלפחד Tzelofchad got a
double portion because of a בכור. bechor.
ותעמודנה לפני משה. Vata’amodnah lifnei Moshe. Now we're going to continue with
the story about בנות צלפחד. benot Tzelofchad. ותעמודנה לפני משה ולפני אלעזר
הכהן ולפני הנשיאים וכל העדה. Vata’amodnah lifnei Moshe v’lifnei Elazar HaKohen v’lifnei
hanesi’im vechol ha’eidah. They stood before משה Moshe and אלעזר Elazar and
the נשיאים, nesi’im, the leaders, and the entire
congregation. אפשר עמדו לפני משה, Efshar amdu lifnei Moshe, etcetera, ולא אמר
להם דבר? velo amar lahem davar? So it assumes it sounds like
it was an order. First they went to משה, Moshe, then they
went to אלעזר, Elazar, then they went to the נשיאים, nesi’im, then
they went to the whole congregation. הגמרא HaGemara says is that really
possible? אפשר
עמדו לפני משה? Efshar amdu lifnei Moshe? They went to משה Moshe
to register their
request, complaint request, ולא אמר להם דבר, velo amar lahem davar, and
he didn't have an
answer. ואחר כך עמדו לפני הנשיאים וכל העדה? V’acharei chen amdu lifnei
hanesi’im vechol ha’eidah? Or maybe it should have been that it was
possible they went to משה Moshe and אלעזר Elazar and they didn't
have the answer. Okay, yeah, it actually should be אלעזר Elazar because
it's ולא אמרו velo amru in plural. So אפשר עמדו לפני משה
ואלעזר ולא אמרו להם דבר? efshar amdu lifnei Moshe v’Elazar velo amru
lahem davar? Is it possible they went to משה Moshe and אלעזר
Elazar and they didn't have the answer? And then they had to—they
went on to the נשיאים? nesi’im? ואמרו לפני וכל העדה? V’amru lifnei
vechol ha’eidah? אלא סירס המקרא ודרשהו דברי רבי יאשיה. Ela seres hamikra
v’darshehu divrei Rabi Yoshiyah. So רבי יאשיה Rabi Yoshiyah says no, no,
no. What it means is they went to משה Moshe after having
first gone to אלעזר, Elazar, and after having first gone to the
נשיאים, nesi’im, and after having first gone to the whole congregation. So
finally they went to משה. Moshe. But when it was going to
say, they didn't want to mention משה Moshe last, it mentioned משה
Moshe first, but the implication is that that's where they went to
after having gone to these previous places. authorities or people without getting
sufficient answers. אבא חנן אמר משום רבי אליעזר בבית המדרש היו יושבים
והלכו ועמדו להם לפני כולם. Abba Chanan amar mishum Rabbi Eliezer b'veit
hamidrash hayu yoshvim vehalkhu ve'amdu lahem lifnei kulam. No, no, no, no,
no, they went and they went up to משה Moshe in the
בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, obviously a little, a little anachronistic, but whatever,
but they went to משה Moshe and everybody happened to be there.
So it wasn't sequential. They went to the whole group of people,
and משה, Moshe, אלעזר, Elazar, and the נשיאים, Nesi'im, the whole עדה
Eidah were there. All right, so it's a question of whether it
was sequential but just listed in the reverse order, or whether it
was actually all at the same time. במאי קמיפלגי? Be-mai kamiflegi? What
are they debating? מר סבר חולקין כבוד לתלמיד במקום הרב Mar savar
cholkin kavod l'talmid b'makom ha-rav ומר סבר אין חולקין. u'mar savar ein
cholkin. The question is whether you show respect
to a תלמיד talmid in the place of the רב, rav, or
whether you don't. If the רבי rebbe is there, you don't recognize
the תלמיד. talmid. So therefore, the one who says that you do
show
respect says that it meant that they came and they were all
there at the same time. And even though they were all there
at the same time, you specifically, you didn't just say they came
to משה. Moshe. Since everybody was there, you acknowledged all the other
people there, all the people of the lesser authorities as well. That's
not considered to be a denigration or a cutting under the status
of משה, Moshe, actually because he's a תלמיד, talmid, he's not a
competing
authority. They are below משה. Moshe. So actually, it's a way of
recognizing משה's Moshe authority by recognizing all these other people who are
also authorities, though under משה. Moshe. So that's the approach, that they
were all there at the same time and you are going to
mention the other people there; you're not going to ignore that. The
other approach said no, if they came at the same time, it
would have just mentioned משה. Moshe. You don't acknowledge the other people
if משה's Moshe there. And the reason therefore the other people were
acknowledged was because it was sequential. The פסוק pasuk is relating it
in reverse order to give respect to משה, Moshe, but the reason
others are mentioned was because they were sequential. If they were there
at the same time, they would not have been mentioned at all.
All right, so מר סבר אין חולקין. mar savar ein cholkin. והלכתא
חולקין והלכתא אין חולקין. ve-hilchasa cholkin ve-hilchasa ein cholkin. The הלכה halacha
is you do show respect and the הלכה halacha is you don't
show respect. קשיא הלכתא אהלכתא? Kashya hilchasa a-hilchasa? So obviously these aren't
contradictory. So הלכתא אהלכתא לא קשיא. hilchasa a-hilchasa lo kashya. הא דפליג
ליה רביה יקרא הא דלא פליג ליה רביה יקרא. Ha d'palig lei
rabeih yikara ha d'lo palig lei rabeih yikara. The question is whether
the רבי rebbe himself shows respect to his תלמיד. talmid. Somebody comes
up to the רבי, rebbe, and the רבי rebbe says to his
תלמיד, talmid, "Oh, how would you answer it?" or "Maybe you'd like
to, you know, לחיים, lechayim, what do you think?" So if the
רבי rebbe has signaled that he wants his תלמיד talmid to be
recognized in his presence, then you mention the תלמיד. talmid. Now you
still mention משה Moshe first, but then you also acknowledge the תלמיד.
talmid. If the רבי rebbe has signaled that he doesn't want the
תלמיד talmid to be recognized in his presence, then you don't. So
you sort of go based on the signals you're receiving from the
רבי. rebbe. Okay. תני, Tani, we taught in a ברייתא. braita. בנות
צלפחד חכמניות הן, Benos Tzelofchad chachmaniyos hen, they were wise. דרשניות הן,
darshaniyos hen, they were good explicators of the פסוקים. pesukim.
צדקניות הן, tzidkaniyos hen, and they were righteous. חכמניות הן, chachmaniyos hen,
they were wise in the sense of, like,
understanding
human dynamics and politics and how to navigate a situation. שלפי שעה
דברו. she-le-fi sha'ah dibru. They waited for the right opening, timing is
everything. You don't just go ahead and make your request; they waited
till it was the right time that their request could be heard.
They were very sort of wise in the ways of the world.
דאמר רבי שמואל בר רב יצחק, d'amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak,
מלמד שהיה משה רבינו יושב ודורש בפרשת יבמים. melamed she-hayah Moshe Rabbeinu
yoshev ve-doresh b'parshat yevamim. I don't know what the מלמד melamed is,
but he's asserting that the story was that they didn't just walk
up to משה Moshe and say, "Hey, we want a portion." They
waited till it was the right time, till משה Moshe was giving
over the פרשה parsha of יבום, yibbum, which appears later in the
תורה. Torah. שנאמר, she-ne'emar, and it says there, כי ישבו אחים יחדיו,
ki yeshvu achim yachdav, when brothers sit together and one of them
dies, and he has no son, it literally says, then
his, the brother-in-law has to do this act of יבום yibbum with
the widow. So
אמרו לו, amru lo, they said to him, אם כבן אנו חשובים,
im ke-ben anu chashuvim, so what's our story when it comes to
יבום? yibbum? Because our father died, he left no sons, he left
daughters. When you say if there's no son, and therefore this act
of יבום yibbum has to do, how do daughters play in? If
we're like a son and we exempt our mother from an act
of יבום, yibbum, which by the way is the actual הלכה, halacha,
אם כבן אנו חשובים תנה לנו נחלה כבן. im ke-ben anu chashuvim
t'nah lanu nachalah ke-ben. So
then, if that's true, then we deserve also an inheritance. If we're
considered like a son for the laws of יבום, yibbum, we should
be considered like a son, at least in the absence of a
son, at least if we, then we should also be considered that
in the laws of inheritance. ואם לאו, ve-im lav, and if not,
תתייבם אמנו, tityabem imenu, let our mother do יבום. yibbum. And since
basically it was clear to them that their mother was not obligated
in יבום, yibbum, they were basically saying, and they didn't say, "Oh,
if our mother isn't obligated in יבום, yibbum, then we have to,
whatever, then we demand an inheritance." that would have been too aggressive
and probably could have evoked a defensive response. It was just simple
just tell us the options are we like a son or not?
If we are, let's get inheritance if not let our mother do
יבום. yibum. Oh, our mother wasn't going to have to do יבום?
yibum? Then we should get an inheritance. And by the way, part
of this now you could say each area of הלכה halacha has
its different parameters, but since the idea of יבום yibum is יקום
על שם אחיו המת yakum al shem achiv hamet and that the
brother-in-law sort of gets the inheritance of the dead brother, then it
is tied in very much to this idea of inheritance and if
we are considered when that a continuation of our father that there's
not a need for the brother-in-law to do, for the father's brother
to do יבום, yibum, so that means that the inheritance is considered
to also continue through us and we should therefore get the inheritance.
Okay, that was their argument. I think the רשב"ם Rashbam says it,
let me just see. Yeah,
yeah, and if you take a look at the—no. Yeah, the רשב"ם
Rashbam says
ובן מונעו מליבם אם לא מירשת אביו ופוטר הוא את אמו ויורש
את אביו. u'ben moneo mi'lyabem im lo miyoreshet aviv v'poter hu et
imo v'yoresh et aviv. Alright, so that it's very much the יבום
yibum idea also as to who is seen as a continuation for
the father, particularly also in terms of the inheritance. So these two
should be intertwined and therefore we should get an inheritance. So they
waited for their right opening. מיד
ויקרב משה את משפטן לפני ה'. Miyad vayakrev moshe et mishpatan lifne
hashem. Moshe realized, oh my god, they have a good point, so
he checked out with, he checked in with God to find out
what the answer was.
דרשניות היו. Darshaniyot hayu. So that was like one was wise in
the ways of the world, but they also were good in terms
of explicators of the text. שהיו אומרות אלו היה לה בן לא
דברנו She'hayu omrot ilu haya la'ben lo dibarnu because they said if
our father had had a son, we would not have spoken. So
what does that mean? It means that
what פסוק pasuk are they exactly דרש-ing? darshan It means like what,
we're not suggesting that we should be equal to the son, but
if there's no son, then we think that we are inherited. So
the רשב"ם Rashbam says well they were דרש-ing darshan the פסוקים psukim
of the נחלה, nachala, אם בן אין לו. im ben ein lo.
The problem is that that פרשה parsha had not been given, it
was only given because of their challenge to Moshe. So תוספות Tosafot
says no, they would have known it either because of the principle
or because of the פסוק pasuk והתנחלתם אתם לבניכם, v'hitnachaltem otam livnechem,
לבניכם ולא לבנותיכם. livnechem v'lo livnotechem. They would have understood that you
could have interpreted the פסוק pasuk to favor sons, okay, or because
of the idea—and this isn't really דרשניות darshaniyot in terms of explicating
text—but they could have understood the idea that a daughter would have
led to the property going out of the tribe. So they understood
enough the way the legal system worked that they said we would
not have asked, either for textual or for other reasons, to have
a portion had there been a son. But there isn't a son,
so that's why we are asking. So they were also very wise
in the way of the legal system. Okay. ובתניא בת? V'tanya bat?
So אמר רבי ירמיה סמי מכאן בת. Amar Rabbi Yirmiya summi mi-kan
bat. So one minute, but we taught a ברייתא braita that says
if there had been a daughter, we would not have asked. That
doesn't make sense, they are daughters. Okay, so we're not challenging the
idea that they were דרשניות, darshaniyot, but what does this ברייתא braita
mean, had there been a daughter we would not have asked? Okay,
so רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya said fine, that's a mistake, get rid
of that ברייתא. braita. אביי אמר אפילו היתה בת לבן לא דברנו.
Abaye amar afilu hayta bat l'ben lo dibarnu. No, no, no, what
it means is is that
we had a brother who had died and he had had a
daughter, we would not have spoken. We understood enough the idea that
the man is privileged in this system to understand that a daughter
of our brother, of a dead brother, would have had precedence over
us. Alright? Because but in the absence of brothers, that's where we
are asking that we deserve a portion.
צדקניות היו, Tzadkaniyot hayu, they were righteous, שלא נישאו אלא להגון להן,
she-lo nisu ela la-hagun la-hen, that they only married those that were
appropriate for them. Because the פסוק pasuk says לטוב בעיניהן תהיינה לנשים,
la-tov b'eineihen tihyena l'nashim, they can marry whoever is good in their
eyes and חז"ל chazal understood that that was not that basically was
עצה טובה, eitza tova, that the פסוק pasuk was saying they should
wait, find somebody who's really appropriate for them and that they actually
did wait and they were not overeager to get married. Alright, so
where do we see that? תניא רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Tanya Rabbi
Eliezer Ben Yaakov, אפילו קטנה שבהן לא ניסת פחות מארבעים שנה. afilu
katana she-bahen lo nises pachos me-arbayim shana. Even the youngest one waited
till she was 40 years old till it was find somebody who
was really appropriate for her in order to marry. תוספות Tosafot also
says this might have been because the story of צלפחד Tzelofchad might
have occurred—צלפחד Tzelofchad might have died at the beginning of the 40
years and this was at the end of the 40 years and
whatever, one way or the other they waited for the right time
to get married. איני? Eini? Is that really true? Would that really
have been wise? ואמר רב חסדא ניסת פחות מבת עשרים יולדת עד
שישים Ve'amar Rav Chisda nises pachos mi-ben esrim yoledes ad shishim if
a woman gets married under 20 she starts having kids right away,
that'll—the assumption here was obviously that whatever, nobody
is—we're not discussing the accuracy of this science, but the assumption is
that that would have led to a life of high fertility
and she would be able to give birth until 60. בת עשרים
יולדת עד ארבעים. bas esrim yoledes ad arbaim. If she waits till
her 20s then she'll be able to give birth till her till
she's in her 40s. בת ארבעים שוב איני יולדת bas arbaim shuv
eini yoledes if she waits till her 40s she won't be able
to give birth at all, that's not true, but whatever, but that's
the גמרא's Gemara's assumption. So how could they have waited till their
40s? Weren't they weren't they be concerned that they would not be
able to have children? אלא מתוך שצדקניות הן ella mitoch shetzidkaniyos hen
נעשה להן נס na'asa lahen nes כי יוכבד ki Yocheved because they
were righteous they were able to have children. They were righteous that
they waited that long and because of their righteousness they were able
to have children
just like יוכבד. Yocheved. דכתיב וילך איש מבית לוי ויקח את בת
לוי dechsiv vayeilech ish mibeis Levi vayikach es bas Levi the famous
דרשה drasha about how old יוכבד Yocheved was, that יוכבד Yocheved was,
we'll see,
130 when she gave birth to משה. Moshe. A man from the
house of לוי Levi went and took the daughter of לוי. Levi.
Top of קכ עמוד א. kof chof amud aleph. אפשר בת, efshar
bas, should you say she was a בת bas meaning a young
person? אפשר בת מאה ושלושים שנה
וקרא לה בת efshar bas me'ah u'sheloshim shanah v'karu lah bas was
it possible somebody who is 130 years old and she's called a
בת bas like she's a young girl? And how do we know
she was 130 when משה Moshe was conceived? דאמר רבי חמא בר
חנינא d'amar Rabbi Chama bar Chanina זו יוכבד שהורתה בדרך ונולדה
בין החומות. zu Yocheved shehorasa baderech venolada bein hachomos. We discussed this
earlier when it counts the children of לאה, Leah, you know, when
it counts the children of יעקב Yaakov it's 69 if you include
יוסף Yosef and his two sons but when it says when they
came to מצרים Mitzrayim they were 70 and the number is off
in the children of לאה Leah so one of the children of
לאה Leah or descendants of לאה Leah has to find that extra
one. So they say that this is יוכבד. Yocheved. It says אשר
ילדה אותה ללוי במצרים asher yulda osah l'Levi b'Mitzrayim you know was
given birth to לוי Levi in מצרים. Mitzrayim. The birth was in
מצרים Mitzrayim but the the pregnancy was out of מצרים. Mitzrayim. So
when they went down they were 69 but when they came to
מצרים Mitzrayim they were 70, she had just been born. So יוכבד
Yocheved was born when they came to מצרים. Mitzrayim. They were in
מצרים Mitzrayim 210 years, משה Moshe was 80, so she was 130
when she conceived משה. Moshe. Okay. ונולדה בין החומות venolada bein hachomos
דכתיב אשר ילדה אותה ללוי במצרים dechsiv asher yulda osah l'Levi b'Mitzrayim
לידתה במצרים והורתה שלא במצרים leidasa b'Mitzrayim vehorasa shelo b'Mitzrayim she was
born in
מצרים Mitzrayim but her pregnancy her mother was pregnant with her out
of מצרים. Mitzrayim. ואמאי קרו לה בת v'amai karu lah bas so
if that's true anyway the point though being for us that she
conceived when she was 130 and actually you know משה Moshe and
מרים Miriam and אהרן Aharon were only a few years older so
already there in her 120s she was giving birth. So clearly because
she was a צדקת tzadikes she gave birth past the age of
40 and these women also because even though their first giving of
birth was you know אהרן Aharon and מרים Miriam and these women
as well because they were צדקניות tzidkaniyos and they waited for the
right man also were able to give birth even though they only
started after 40. Now just finishing this point. ואמאי קרו לה בת
v'amai karu lah bas why was she called a בת bas if
she was you know suggests young? אמר רב יהודה בר זבידא amar
Rav Yehuda bar Zvida מלמד שנולדו לה סימני נערות melamed shenoldu lah
simanei naarus that when she was
retaken by עמרם Amram for you know
they had already been married but it was like a remarriage because
they had separated because of the גזירה gezira of פרעה Paroh and
anyway then when he retook her she had become like you know
her youth had restored to her sort of like by שרה. Sarah.
נתעדן
הבשר nisaden habasar the the flesh became you know supple. נתפשטו הקמטים
nispashtu haktatim the the wrinkles smoothed out. וחזר היופי למקומו vechazar hayofi
limkomo her beauty came back to the way it used to be.
Okay and now we're going to just finish up this story again
famous מדרש. midrash. ויקח vayikach he took her as a wife. ויחזיר
מיבעי ליה vayachzir mibei leh he should have said he took her
back because you know she had already given birth to מרים Miriam
and אהרן. Aharon. אמר רב יהודה בר זבידא amar Rav Yehuda bar
Zvida מלמד שעשה בה מעשה ליקוחין melamed she'asa bah ma'aseh likuchin he
you know he made a whole new wedding for her it was
like it was a second marriage not second whatever you know a
reestablishing of the vows they did a whole wedding ceremony. הושיבה באפריון
hoshivah b'apiryon had her sit in a type of a
carriage. ואהרן ומרים משוררים לפניה v'Aharon u'Miriam meshorerin l'faneha and אהרן Aharon
and מרים Miriam were rejoicing in front of her. ומלאכי השרת אומרים
אם הבנים שמחה u'mal'achei hashareis omrim eim habanim simeichah and the mother
of the children is rejoicing mother of already two children and then
will be giving birth to משה. Moshe. So this all of course
ties into the מדרש midrash where you know when פרעה Paroh said
that כל הבן הילוד היאורה תשליכוהו kol haben hayilod haye'orah tashlichuhu he
separated from יוכבד Yocheved excuse me not אהרן Aharon when עמרם Amram
he separated from יוכבד Yocheved and then מרים Miriam you know מרים
Miriam had a
prophesied that you know that in the that through her mother the
redeemer would be born משה Moshe would be born because it says
you know it says by מרים Miriam מרים הנביאה אחות אהרן Miriam
hanevia achos Aharon that she had been a prophet when she was
only the sister of אהרן Aharon before משה Moshe had been born.
She prophesied the redeemer would be born through her mother and also
she said to her father what you're doing is worse than פרעה.
Paroh. פרעה's Paroh only doing it for the men, you know you're
separating and now everybody in the country of our people are following
your example is separating it means there'll be no men and no
born you know פרעה Paroh you don't know whether it's going to
what will be the end of his
And then as her father listened to her, so interesting, listened to
her wisdom, listened to her prophecy and took back יוכבד, Yocheved, actually
yes, and took back יוכבד Yocheved and through that משה Moshe was
conceived, which is the end of this story. So again, a sort
of story about the wisdom and the righteousness of women against sort
of the, I guess, sort of almost like the sort of rigidity
of men, interesting parallel between the story of יוכבד Yocheved and עמרם
Amram and בנות צלפחד Bnot Tzelofchad and משה. Moshe. Okay, we'll end
here.